Vipul Bhagwat

Pune • vipulbhagwat1999@gmail.com • 8600265159 • LinkedIn • Portfolio

Professional Summary (DevOps Engineer)

A dedicated DevOps Engineer with 4 years of experience in automating, optimizing, and building cloud infrastructure, CI/CD pipelines, and containerized environments. Strong background in Kubernetes, Terraform, Ansible and Observability. Proven success in leading automation initiatives at Qualys, driving substantial efficiency improvements and cost optimization.

Experience

Qualys (A company specializing in cloud-based security solutions to manage and mitigate cyber risks) **DevOps Engineer**June 2024 – Current

- Led setup of Kubernetes on Hybrid and On-Premise environments for running 100+ microservices, while ensuring scalability, reliability, and high availability.
- Leveraged Helm to automate and reduce microservices deployment time to under 1 min, significantly improving operational efficiency.
- Automated Kubernetes upgrades using CI/CD and Ansible playbooks.
- Implemented Ceph CSI for dynamic provisioning of persistent volumes.
- Automated infrastructure provisioning with Terraform for consistent deployments.
- Optimized OKE worker node autoscaling, reducing costs by 50% while improving performance.
- Addressed Kubernetes security vulnerabilities and enforced security using RBAC and admission controllers.
- Provisioned and integrated GPUs into Kubernetes for AI/ML workloads.
- Streamlined OKE setup automation for efficient cluster management.
- Managed HashiCorp Vault for secure secret storage and integrated it with Kubernetes secrets.
- Migrated from Docker to CRI-O for improved Kubernetes container runtime efficiency.
- Improved software delivery efficiency through collaboration with development teams.
- Developed ad-hoc Jenkins pipelines for devops components maintenance and binary upgrades.
- Implemented HPA to optimize resource consumption, resulting in a 40% reduction in resource usage.

Qualys

SRE DevOps Engineer

Aug 2021 - May 2024

- Led Kubernetes cluster management, including scaling, upgrades, and troubleshooting, ensuring high availability.
- Integrated Prometheus and Grafana for real-time monitoring, alerting, and visualizing system health and performance metrics.
- Contributed to distroless image setup and configured them for Kubernetes compatibility for app teams.
- Performed system upgrades, patching, and security audits on Linux-based systems.
- Collaborated with teams to troubleshoot and resolve DevOps-related issues.
- Assisted in containerizing Java Spring Boot applications and deploying them on Kubernetes.
- Migrated DevOps components from on-premises to Oracle Cloud Infrastructure (OCI).
- Administered Vault, Consul, and Nexus for secure secrets management, service discovery, and artifact storage.
- Worked on securing infrastructure for Fedramp Audits.

Qualys

DevOps Intern

March 2021 – Aug 2021

- Developed a Python-based web app to monitor DevOps components in dev and QA environments.
- Automated certificate renewal using Ansible playbooks and a Jenkins pipeline.

Technical Skills

- Containerization & Orchestration: Kubernetes, Docker, Helm
- Cloud Platforms: Oracle Cloud, AWS, Vsphere(On Premise)
- Infrastructure as Code (IaC): Terraform, Ansible
- CI/CD Tools: Jenkins
- Secrets Management: Hashicorp Vault
- Artifact Repositories: Nexus
- Programming Languages: Python, Go, Shell Scripting
- Operating Systems: Linux (RedHat, CentOS, OEL, Ubuntu)
- Observability: Prometheus, Grafana, Alertmanager
- Networking: Nginx, DNS, Load Balancers
- Version Control Tools: Git (Bitbucket and Github)
- IDEs: Visual Studio Code
- Atlassian Tools: JIRA, Confluence
- Scaled Agile Methodologies
- Quick Learner, with strong communication, collaboration, active listening, and problem-solving skills

Education

Pimpri Chinchwad College of Engineering, Pune

B.E, Computer Engineering. 71.8%

Certifications/Courses

Graduation Date: June 2021

- Certified Kubernetes Administrator (CKA) (Scored 100%) here
- HashiCorp Certified: Terraform Associate Cert Prep by KodeKloud
- Learning HashiCorp Vault (Linkedin)

Projects

• K8sCapacity – Kubernetes Cluster Capacity Checker
Developed a command-line tool, **k8scapacity**, using Golang to analyze Kubernetes cluster capacity.